A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980 FA739G
Rockefeller Archive Center
- The uses of higher education, October 8 (Reports 019025), 1965; Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley)
  Gathering rites; Universities and colleges -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States
- Technology and timidity in education, November 19 (Reports 019026), 1965; Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley)
  "Technology and education go hand in hand, and their relationship has become considerably more intimate in the last decade." [p. 1]
  Technology -- Education -- United States
- Speech on private foundations (Reports 019027), 1972; Heard, Alexander
  "Foundations are private, nonprofit organizations set up as corporations or trusts, usually under state laws, to receive and distribute funds for the advancement of human welfare." [p. 1]
- The role of private philanthropy in the newly developing nations, February 24 (Reports 019028), 1960; Hill, F. F. (Forrest Frank)
  Private American philanthropy has long concerned itself with the problems of the less economically developed parts of the world. [p. 1]
- Family structure and dynamics of fertility control, May 9 (Reports 019029), 1966; Hill, Reuben
  Lecture to Seminar on Population Dynamics, Johns Hopkins University.
  Population
- Remarks on the Foundation at Civic Center, Pasadena, CA, April 24 (Reports 019030), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  The Foundation satisfies in many the traditional American love of superlatives. [p. 2]
- Address at the Victory dinner of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Development Program, May 4 (Reports 019031), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "I would like to discuss with you this evening one of these basic shifts in the American pattern. It is a shift that already has had a great impact on our way of life, and in my opinion will have an even greater impact in the years ahead." [p. 2]
- Remarks on communism and capitalism, June 12 (Reports 019032), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "If we businessmen -- of whatever country -- want a verdict in our favor, we had better convince the jury of people all over the world that the economic system of which we are a part will do more for them than any other system..." [p. 3]
  Business; Communism; Capitalism
- Remarks at Centennial International YMCA Convention, Cleveland, OH, June 22 (Reports 019033), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "As we all know, democracy comes from two Greek words signifying power of the people. For that reason we to think of democracy primarily as a polical matter." [p. 1]
  Democracy -- United States
- Address before the National Association of Life Underwriters, Los Angeles, CA, September 19 (Reports 019034), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Let me deal first with the question of World War III. I am aware of all the dangers. [p. 2]
  Cold War
- Remarks at Rotary Club of Padena, September 26 (Reports 019035), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "Today we are painfully conscious that the river Yangtze flows down Main Street, and that the river Han in Korea also flows down Main Street, and so does the Rhine, the Seine, and the Volga." [p. 2]
- Address at Westwood Community Methodist church, Los Angeles, September 30 (Reports 019036), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "The largest obstacle to the achievement of peace is, of course, the determination of the Russian leaders to force their Godless way of life upon the rest of the world." [p. 1]
- Address to Automoile Old timers, Detroit, MI, October 4 (Reports 019037), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "The record of cooperation in the automotive industries is as outstanding as the record of competition, and equally important." [p. 4]
  Automobile industry and trade -- United States
- Address at Freedom House Award, October 7 (Reports 019038), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Freedom is concerned with maintenance of freedom and with the maintenance and perfection of a free society. [p. 1]
- Address at Harvard business School Club of New York, New York City, October 9 (Reports 019039), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "...For between the end of World War II and the start of the Marshall Plan in the spring of 1948, not only had the countries of Eastern Europe fallen under Soviet sway, but also during this same perioud Mao tse Tund in China, using compas and T-square mad
  International relations; Economic assistance -- Europe
- Address at Wendell L. Willkie Memorial Program, October 18 (Reports 019040), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  The people were right. In that great heart of Wendell Willkie there was a deep love for people -- the people of his home town of Rushville... [p. 1]
- Memorial address for Senator A. Vandenberg at Grand Rapids Council on World Affairs, October 19 (Reports 019041), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "Senator Vandenberg was one of those great men whose heart was for all men and who will live in the hearts of men everywhere, because he understood so deeply that the long-range self-interest of his country lay in peace, justice and freedom for all men...
- Address at New York Herald Tribune Forum, New York, NY, October 24 (Reports 019042), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Any plan to relieve tensions in the world today must take into account the hard and relentless determination of the Soviet overlords to CREATE tensions. [p. 1]
  International relations; Cold War
- Address at Los Angeles Council of Church Women, November 2 (Reports 019043), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "...In some countries any kind of peace is acceptable, but we in the free world insist that peace must be based on freedom and justice." [p. 1]
- Address at National Institute of Social Sciences, New York, NY, November 8 (Reports 019044), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G. (Box 890)
  "To wage the peace intelligently, we must recognize the nature of the danger which surrounds us." [p. 3]
- Remarks at National Conference of Christians and Jews, November 15 (Reports 019045), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "Our greatest danger today is that we will act as a frightened people, and that the sense of insecurity that has enshrouded us will lead us to acts of desperation." [p. 1]
- Our common cause, November 28 (Reports 019046), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Address at English Speaking Union.
- Address at First International Conference of Manufacturers, New York City, December 3 (Reports 019047), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "People who have been slumbering through the centuries are not awakening and saying, "We want a better life." In Europe and here in American the great mass of pople are demanding a better life." [p. 3]
  International relations; Manufacturing industries
- Quest for peace, December 11 (Reports 019048), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Address at Institute of World Affairs, Riverside, CA.
- Address at Commonwealth Club, San Francisco, CA, December 21 (Reports 019049), 1951; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "Each of the 361 days that has come and gone since Christmas 1950 has brought with it reports and rumors of conflicts -- crises, tensions and outright warfare." [p. 1]
- Address at Ebell Club of Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA, January 2 (Reports 019050), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "During the past quarter of a century, we have lived in a continuing atmosphere of tension. As we entered upon each year, we have been solemnly to that it was the year of decision." [p. 1]
- Address at Automobile Old timers, San Francisco, CA, January 4 (Reports 019051), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  The America of the early nineteen hundreds was a very different America than that which had emerged by the mid-century of 1950. [p. 1]
- The world outlook, January 10 (Reports 019052), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Address at the Business Outlook Conference of the Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce, Los Angeles, CA.
- Address at Wellesley Club of southern California, Pasadena, CA., January 28 (Reports 019053), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "If anyone suggested a generation ago that in 1952 the most pervasive influence in our lives would be exercised by a small group of second-rate men located in Moscow, Russia, we would have thought it a huge joke." [p. 1]
- Address at Catholic Press Council of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA., February 15 (Reports 019054), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "And yet today that small group of men in the Kremlin, as a result of their determined efforts to force their tyrannical way of life on the rest of the world, has a most pervasive influence on your daily life and mine." [p. 1]
- Address at National Conference of Christians and Jews, Los Angeles, CA., February 28 (Reports 019055), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "The basic cause of world tensions is, of course, the determination of the men in the Kremlin to force their tyrannical way of life on the rest of the world." [p. 1]
- Address at Foundation for Freedom Institute, UCLA., March 1 (Reports 019056), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Two world wars are still green in our memories. We are living under the threat of a third great war. We are also living with the nightmare horror of the atom bomb. [p. 1]
- Address at Philadelphia Bulletin Forum, Philadelphia, PA, March 4 (Reports 019057), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "The most obvious block to peace at the present time is, of course, the determination of the men in the Kremlin to force their tyrannical way of life on the rest of the world." [p. 1]
- Address at New Hampshire Hall, University of New Hampshire, Duram, NH, March 5 (Reports 019058), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "...With many of them fighting and dying in Korea -- all these are the result of our failure, so far, to stop the drive of the Kremlin to impose their own tyrannical way of life on the rest of the world." [p. 5]
  International relations; Cold War; Campaign management
- Address at Women's National Press Club, Washington, D. C., April 16 (Reports 019059), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "Unfortunately, it is impossible for most of the peoples outside the Soviet orbit to see how these yearnings for peace and for a better tomorrow can be realized unless and until the rulers of the Russian people abandon their plans to force their tyrannica
- Peace can be now, April 29 (Reports 019060), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "There are those who believe that that drive can be halted only by another general World War. That there is danger of our becoming invloved in another World War, no one can deny." [p. 1]
- A business statesman looks at the world, May 27 (Reports 019061), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "There are those who believe that that drive can be halted only by another general World War. That there is danger of our becoming invloved in another World War, no one can deny." [p. 3]
- Address at Michigan State College, East Lansing, MI, June 8 (Reports 019062), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  I am appreciative of having been invited to speak at this commencement exercise of Michigan State College for a number of reasons... [p. 1]
  Baccalaureate addresses -- Michigan State College; International relations; Cold War
- Address at General Council of Congregational Churches, Claremont, CA, June 23 (Reports 019063-001), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "Men yearn for peace but they still fear, suspect and hate some of their fellow men, particularly those who live beyond the borders of their own country." [p. 1]
- USA - not confidential, September 25 (Reports 019063-002), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Address at American Automobile Association, Washington, D. C.
  Opportunity -- United States; Women -- United States; Automobile industry and trade
- Address at Economic Club of Southwestern Michigan, St. Joseph, MI, October 30 (Reports 019064), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "The picture of 1900 would not be complete, however, unless we found how people on the other side of the tracks were living." [p. 2]
  Opportunity -- United States; Education -- United States; Economic development -- United States; International relations; Cold War
- Address at St. Andrews Society, New York City, December 1 (Reports 019065), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "The real glory of this land we live in, the underlying fact which totally justifies it, is that here men have had a constantly expanding opportunity to realize on their capacities, intellectually and spiritually as well as materially." [p. 2]
- Address at the Annual Meeting of the Institute of Life Insurance, Waldorf-Astoria, New York, December 11 (Reports 019066), 1952; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "Our capitalism is unique, too, in its capacity for growth. It doesn't just exists, it evolves, meeting changing conditions with changing methods." [p. 1]
  Capitalism; Communism
- U.S.A. -- not confidential, January 16 (Reports 019067), 1953; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "Out of these varied experiences has come the realization that business, government, and philanthropy have one strong bond in common." [p. 1]
  Capitalism; Economic development
- Address before Los Angeles Realty Board, Los Angeles, CA, February 11 (Reports 019068), 1953; Hoffman, Paul G.
  "We speak of our economic system as capitalistic. But any resemblance it bears to many of the capitalistic system in other parts of the world is, as they say "purely coincidental"." [p. 2]
  Capitalism; Economic development; Communism
- Voluntaryism -- the strength of America, February 16 (Reports 019069), 1953; Hoffman, Paul G.
  There is a point about our free enterprise system that should be made at the outset. [p. 2]
- The less-developed countries - our new frontier, June 8 (Reports 019070), 1959; Hoffman, Paul G.
  Developing countries -- Economic conditions
- Some thoughts on early schooling, May 21 (Reports 019071), 1971; Howe, Harold, II
  Remarks to Council of Foundations Meeting in Montreal.
  Early childhood education -- United States; Education, Preschool -- United States; Poor children -- United States; Education -- Disadvantaged children
- Graduate address -- Dickinson College, Carlisle, PA, May 23 (Reports 019072), 1971; Howe, Harold, II
  Baccalaureate addresses -- Dickinson College; Poverty -- International cooperation
- Tennis and teaching -- revisited, September 1 (Reports 019073), 1971; Howe, Harold, II
  Remarks to AASA - NASE Seminar for Dean of Education in Las Vegas, NV.
  Teachers -- Training of -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States; Education -- United States
- Public education for a humane society, November 20 (Reports 019074), 1972; Howe, Harold, II
  "It would be easy to use our time at ths meeting reviewing the shortcomings of American society and its public and private leaders in moving toward the ideal of quality, integrated education." [p. 1]
  Education -- United States; School integration -- United States
- Testimony of Harold Howe II to the Education Subcommittee on the United States Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare (Reports 019075), 1973; Howe, Harold, II
  Women -- Education -- United States
- The forces for change in tuition policies and student aid, October 30 (Reports 019076), 1973; Howe, Harold, II
  In the United States we have two distinct and contrasting traditions for charging students the cost of higher education. [p. 1]
  Tuition -- Education, Higher -- United States
- The access of minorities to higher education (Reports 019077), 1974; Howe, Harold, II
  There is no country in the world that will not sooner or later contend with the perplexing problems created by the demand of excluded groups--usually minorities--for their fair share of the privileges accruing to those who have the opportunity for...
  Minorities -- Education, Higher -- United States
- The role of experience in education, October 8 (Reports 019078), 1974; Howe, Harold, II
  "These little nuggets of elusive meaning may offer useful rallying points for their respective enthusiasts, but many of them fail to communicate with the large universe of people interested in education." [p. 1]
  Experience -- Education -- United States
- Testimony before the Senate Subcommittee on Foundations, the Honorable Vance Hartke, Chairman, November 25 (Reports 019079), 1974; Howe, Harold, II
- Testimony before the Senate Subcommittee on Select Education, the Honorable John Brademas, Chairman, November 4 (Reports 019080), 1974; Howe, Harold, II
  Education -- Law and legislation -- United States
- The value of college as seen by a non-economist, November 10 (Reports 019081), 1975; Howe, Harold, II
  Value -- Education -- United States
- Environment for change in higher education (Reports 019082), 1976; Howe, Harold, II
  Planning is now vastly more sophisticated than anything The Ford Foundation required ten years ago. [p. 1]
  Educational planning -- United States; Education -- United States; Howe, Harold, II
- Leadership in higher education, October 7 (Reports 019083), 1976; Howe, Harold, II
  It is no news to anyone here that heading a college or university is more difficult and demanding today than it was in the 1950s and early 1960s. [p. 2]
  Educational leadership -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States
- Progress report: the advisory panel on score decline, October 26 (Reports 019084), 1976; Howe, Harold, II
  Presented at the Annual Meeting of the College Entrance Examination Board in New York City. [p. 1]
  Education, Higher -- United States; Universities and colleges -- Entrance examinations
- Citizens, education and schooling, April 20 (Reports 019085), 1977; Howe, Harold, II
  The public schools need thoughtful friends today more than at any time in my experience. They are beset by problems they cannot solve and by insistent questions they cannot answer to the satisfaction of those who raise the questions. [p. 1]
  Education -- United States; Public schools -- United States; Educational change -- United States
- Is it the kids - or us? Thoughts on youth and liberal learning, January 25 (Reports 019086), 1978; Howe, Harold, II
  "There are few universal truths in human affairs, but one of the few is that older persons frequently complain about the young." [p. 1]
  Youth -- Education -- United States; Education, Humanistic -- Childhood and youth
- Tests and schooling (Reports 019087), 1978; Howe, Harold, II
  Address at the National Conference on Achievement Testing, Washington, D. C.
  Achievement tests -- United States; Education -- United States
- Tuning the past to the future - the job of trusteeship, March 2 (Reports 019088), 1978; Howe, Harold, II
  Remarks at a Trustee Dinner of the National Association of Independent Schools, New York Ciy.
  Trusts and trustees -- Education -- United States
- Testimony before the House Subcommittee on Elementary, Secondary, and Vocational Education regarding proposed "Truth in Testing Legislation," H.R. 3564 and H.R. 4949, October 11 (Reports 019089), 1979; Howe, Harold, II
  Academic achievement -- Testing; Education -- United States
- In praise of troublemakers, June 7 (Reports 019090), 1979; Howe, Harold, II
  Remarks at Graduation ceremonies and the Inauguration of Joshua L. Smith as President of the Borough of Manhattan Community College at the Riverside Church in New York City
  Baccalaureate addresses -- Borough of Manhattan Community College; College presidents -- Inauguration; Education, Higher -- United States
- The needs of the inner city -- a total view, April 27 (Reports 019091), 1961; Hunter, David R. (David Romeyn), 1916-2000
  "This is the place where crime rates are highest, where juvenile delinquency is most, where 75% and 80% of the children don't finish high school, where people are poorest, where the color scheme is different from the suburb,..." [p. 1]
  Inner cities -- United States
- Slums and social work or wishes and the double negative, May 31 (Reports 019092), 1962; Hunter, David R. (David Romeyn), 1916-2000
  "Those two boys epitomize all these things. They are lower class, they use double negatives;their opportunities are blocked because they are Negro,..." [p. 2]
  African Americans -- United States; Youth -- United States
- Concepts of responsibility, November 27 (Reports 019093), 1962; Hunter, David R. (David Romeyn), 1916-2000
  "The big, big picture, of course, is the world, issues of war and peace, issues of poverty and ignorance about the majority of the people in the world, issues of the rising expectations of the have-nots." [p. 2]
  Moral responsibility -- United States; Opportunity -- United States; African Americans -- Social conditions -- United States
- Present organization and distribution of youth services, November 29 (Reports 019094), 1962; Hunter, David R. (David Romeyn), 1916-2000
  "The first topic I would like to talk about is the two faces of youth: youth as youth, and youth in transition to adulthood." [p. 1]
  Youth -- United States; Youth development -- United States
- Who's got the action? -- welfare planning in the city, January 24 (Reports 019095), 1963; Hunter, David R. (David Romeyn), 1916-2000
  Perhaps it would help us to get a line on all this by looking at some of the big problems besetting the American city today and thinking a little bit about how welfare councils fit in. [p. 2]
  Public welfare -- United States; Community welfare councils -- United States; Education -- United States; Unemployment -- United States; Poverty -- United States
- Statement for the Subcommittee on Employment and Manpower of the Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, August 7 (Reports 019096), 1963; Hunter, David R. (David Romeyn), 1916-2000
  "It is appropriate to consider these two subjects together because they are inextricably linked in real life. This is not to say that unemployment causes delinquency, nor that delinquents are always unemployed." [p. 2]
  Juvenile delinquency -- United States -- Prevention; Youth -- Services for -- United States; Unemployment -- United States
- Address at Pasadena Chamber of Commerce Annual Banquet, Huntington Hotel, Pasadena, CA, April 4 (Reports 019097), 1952; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-1977
  For centuries men have thought that democracy was possible only if the people were educated. But now we must ask whether the people can be educated in a democracy. [p. 3]
- Address at Town Hall, Biltmore Hotel, Los Angeles, CA, July 21 (Reports 019098), 1953; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-1977
  "...Yet the patriotism of the Los Angeles School Board was so intense that it developed an X-ray eye that enabled it to see Henry Ford II, Benson Ford, Donald David of the Harvard School of Business..." [p. 1]
  Education -- United States; Endowments -- Ford Foundation; Education -- Los Angeles (Calif.) -- United States
- The administrator reconsidered, September 19 (Reports 019099), 1955; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-1977
  Remarks at American College of Hospital Administrators, Atlantic City, NJ.
  College administrators -- United States; Universities and colleges -- United States
- Address at the Commencement Exercises, Hunter College, June 13 (Reports 019100), 1957; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-1977
  Baccalaureate addresses -- Hunter College; Education -- United States
- The economics of recorded music, May 21 (Reports 019101), 1970; Kapp, Richard P.
  Speech given at NMC Annual Meeting at Julliard School.
  Sound recording industry -- United States
- Summary of talk "American balance sheet in Europe," October 16 (Reports 019102), 1951; Katz, Milton
  "In the grim alignment of forces in the world today, the Soviet Union and its satellites have the advantage of numbers." [p. 1]
  Cold War; International relations
- Summary of talk at Pomona College," March 13 (Reports 019103), 1952; Katz, Milton
  "In the grim alignment of forces in the world today, the Soviet Union and its satellites have the advantage of numbers." [p. 2]
- Address at Occidental College, May 8 (Reports 019104), 1952; Katz, Milton
  We naturally want the foreign policy of our government to reflect these purposes. [p. 2]
- The question of peace, June 4 (Reports 019105), 1952; Katz, Milton
  Address at California Institute of Technology Alumni Association, Los Angeles Athletic Club.
- The objectives of American foreign policy and the United Nations, November 17 (Reports 019106), 1952; Katz, Milton